all right great I think I've almost got
you all your first let's get the
pronouns out of the way what would you
prefer I told you professor dr. Jordan
Jordans fine
Jordan's fine I like it that way as well
um Jordan my first question for you and
the reaction here in New Zealand to the
very idea that you're coming here or
that you're fronting on this show today
I just gotta say and I've watched you
for a couple of years you are one of the
most hated people online why do you
think it is that well
I'm hated by a very small minority of
very noisy and committed people yeah and
so they're noisy and committed and so
they can make a lot of racket and they
are very good at it and oftenly perfet
often professionally trained to do so
and they're very casual with their what
would you call it epithets I mean I was
listening to you introduce me and you
you listed off about 20 terrible things
that I might be many of which were
contradictory but that doesn't seem to
make any difference what so selearis you
you kind of get your celebrity gets
co-opted from people on all sorts of
parts of the political spectrum and
extremes of the political spectrum
doesn't it well I think there's some of
that I don't know if it gets co-opted
too much on the radical left let's say
although I certainly face the majority
of my opposition from the radical left
but the radical right types are not very
fond of me either there was a new book
written called Dianetics by a rather
reprehensible individual named Vox Dei
and if you want to find out what the
ethno-nationalism out me that's pretty
good read I wouldn't call it precisely
complementary look on a personal level
and I'm someone who has fallen foul of
the vagaries of Twitter pylons but
what's directed at you is at a whole
different level Jordan and you've
admitted I know that you have or not
struggle but you admit you've had
episodes of depression in your life I
know people who have been horribly
affected by the most minor pile on on
social media
how do you as an individual take or
channel that hatred to good and I
imagine it affects your family as well
well part of it is that I have a pretty
solid family you know I have lots of
people behind me like my wife is firmly
behind me without hesitation my children
are behind me and they're smart and
mature and my parents are behind me and
I have a good set of friends and also
generally I try not to talk about things
that I don't know something about which
also helps yeah so and I'm not impressed
with the sorts of ideological positions
that have been put forth especially by
the left-wing radical types in the
universities and I understand what
they're doing and why reasonably well
and I feel that whatever vitriol happens
to be directed at me is trivial in terms
of its danger in comparison to the
overwhelming social danger that these
ideologies are producing and so better
to do something about it now than to
wait also in a social media world that
is dominated by extremism and hatred and
vitriol people I know who have have
watched you are literally dumbstruck by
your ability to remain civil and to
engage in debate without getting angry
at those who who often absolutely
lambaste you I think I've only seen
there was a debate you did with Stephen
Fry where an American pastor had to go
and I think I saw some fire there I
think you were genuinely upset but you
seem to have a remarkable remarkable
ability to play the ball not the man or
woman
well that debate the Munk debate that
you're talking about mostly I was upset
about the foolishness you know the the
person I was debating with call owed me
an angry white man and it just struck me
is so so rhetorically foolish and
inflammatory and unnecessary all of
those things at the same time first of
all he was in Canada and
not in the United States and those sorts
of statements actually don't go over
very well in Canada and my race had
absolutely nothing to do with what we
were talking about and so it was just
the kind of troublemaking statement that
does nothing but make things worse and
I'm never happy when I see people
behaving in a manner that only makes
things worse and so that that and I felt
even it's a funny thing I can't say
exactly felt bad for him but I thought
it was so foolish of him to undermine
his own credibility in that manner it
was just the sort of performance that
removes all patience you know a bad
rhetorical statement and unnecessary
racist comment a rhetorical flourish
that had nothing but counterproductive
consequences as you can see by the
YouTube commentary added nothing at all
that was productive to the debate didn't
address the issues at hand was a cheap
method of scoring points a way of
playing victim I mean it was altogether
a second great performance and and
because he had academic pretensions was
a professor I have a lot less patience
for professors and professional
journalists than I do for you know other
people because well because they're
they're supposed to well that's their
profession I thought Stephen Fry was
brilliant in that debate and he started
out soggy didn't agree with a lot of
what you said but he was gonna stand
next to you and fight you aside and he
also said I'm the world would be a much
better place if everyone was less
convinced of how right they were
yeah well Stephen Fry is really
something it was a pleasure to meet him
and he's he's quite the remarkable
person so that was one of the very good
things about that evening we're gonna
take a break Jordan and then I want to
talk to you about an interview I did
yesterday and if that's typical of the
stuff that you get yeah that was the
interview man we would dr. Jordan B
Peterson here I made you talk Beth and
just to see and we would talk to Jordan
B Peterson cultural phenomenon and
according to Oakland Peace Action the
biggest threat to New Zealand's way of
life and civilization that I don't know
we've seen since the last earthquake
they
came out earlier this week and threw a
lot of labels at dr. Peterson and the
aspo --cz Minh iris or spokesperson iris
came on with me yesterday simply so I
could ask them to well provide the proof
of their accusations I didn't think he
did that well or they did that well
Jordan well it was quite the remarkable
interview I think that I don't know how
many people have watched it but I
listened to it but I suspect quite a few
and it's no wonder because it was it was
a real feat of journalistic persistence
I would say on your part you didn't let
your your interviewee off the hook for a
moment and there wasn't much content
there there was a lot of exactly the
same sort of thing that's been happening
for the last two years it's really quite
appalling and that what seems to happen
generally in the journalistic sphere on
the negative side for me is that there's
a list of epithets that are it's like
all the radical leftists have a list of
epithets that are sort of at hand maybe
they have them on a little sticky on
their computer misogynist homophobe
Islamophobe transform bigoted racist
then there's often some either Nazi I
don't forget you can addiction either
location there know that and and or
there's Jewish Hill which is another one
that comes up now and then and the idea
seems to be that if you don't agree with
what someone says that you just lay out
the longest possible list of pejoratives
that your imagination your collective
imagination can generate and hope that
one of them is sufficiently true in some
sense because of something you once said
that it sticks and you're done and it's
it's getting downright dull I mean well
I decide that it seems to me that
liberal journalists throughout the
Western world have been lining up to try
and take you down yeah well I mean I've
had a fair number of journalists who
being supportive supportive of me now
whether or not they are on the liberal
side they're certainly not on the
radical left side yes this has been
happening pretty much non-stop for too
years and they're basically out of
insults as far as I can tell which in
some sense disarms them but they're
actually getting rather dull to read
because it's always the same old thing
although the person you interviewed
yesterday did have a new twist which was
greatest threat to the civilization of
New Zealand which was really quite
impressive as far as pejoratives went
alright so we've dealt with Auckland
piece action I know you're in Australia
now has the if you like the violent
opposition to you for whatever reason is
it starting to subside and I know they
haven't been protests as I understand so
far in Australia there was a few in
Adelaide but about twenty five and and
and they it wasn't exactly clear what
they were protesting they seem to be
more concerned about homosexual rights
which I don't really know what that has
to do with me but it had to do with
whatever they were interested in
protesting but there was nothing in
Melbourne at all though there was quite
a large police presence at the venue
while there were a lot of people there
was about 5,500 people but there wasn't
a single protester and I would say that
yes overall the virulence and also the
frequency of the hit pieces in the media
is has declined rather precipitously in
the last three or four months and I
think it's because well because it's
become dreadfully repetitious and
because no smoking pistol of any sort
has emerged you know people have gone
over virtually everything I've said to
students for the last 20 years because
almost all of it is recorded and scoured
my twitter feed and my facebook and you
know all the social media platforms that
are usable and haven't been able to find
anything so far that's of sufficient
reprehensibility to take my reputation
out but the dot so that we had Jordan
come on yellow yeah well it's not just a
bit weird it's it's very weird but you
know it's not
something I were absent
let's say alright um I want to go back
two years and in many ways I look at you
and if I was gonna put you in a fable
you're the guy who said the emperor has
no clothes the Emperor of woke nurse of
political correctness of third wave
feminism did you plan two years ago to
be where you are now a cultural for not
global cultural phenomenon was it all
part of some some clever manipulation of
you know modern social media or did you
just stand up and say I'm not gonna do
this well I mean I was writing a book
and I was hoping it would be successful
so there was that and you know I had
been experimenting quite substantially
with with YouTube putting my my lectures
from the University on YouTube and some
lectures that I had done for a small
television show and they were developing
a certain following so I had about a
million views far before the political
controversy hit but no I mean there's no
way of predicting what happened it's
it's it's a completely unpredictable
phenomena but phenomenon but I can't and
say that I said what I felt like saying
as carefully as I possibly could and I'd
pretty much had enough of it I mean
seriously I've had enough of it and I'm
not happy with the radical leftists I
think the postmodern philosophy is what
intellectually vapid nihilistic
malevolent destructive arrogant and
narcissistic impractical as well all at
the same time I think that what's
happening to the humanities and Social
Sciences is borders on fraudulently
criminal if it hasn't already passed the
line and I'm absolutely no friend
whatsoever of radical leftist utopians
I I feel that there's after a hundred
years of evidence of complete bloody
catastrophe on the side of the radical
left it's time for us to wake up and
notice that something has gone wrong on
that end of the spectrum
and I don't see any responsibility being
taken for that at all
you know I've called publicly for the
moderate leftist types who might have
some sympathy for to draw some lines
it's like all right we know that things
can go too far on the left when exactly
where where is it that you go too far
now my sense it's with the equity
doctrine which I think is not really
emotionally powerful unfortunately it
doesn't have that that that kick that's
necessary to make something really stick
in the memory but I think the idea of
equality of outcome is dangerous beyond
comprehension all right I want to talk
about a few things going on in New
Zealand which is you know part of the
culture wall we're part of the global
community and we connected online a fist
up we have a cabinet the Labour Party
the largest member of our or part of our
coalition government it has a quota a
male/female quota for cabinet posts yeah
- yeah what do you think of that I think
there's absolutely no excuse for it I
think that it's an it's a you know the
the radical leftists are always
yammering on about biological
essentialism make which they associate
with something akin to fascism you know
the idea that there are mutable
biological characteristics that define
people and yet they're the first people
to insist that if you're going to have a
cabinet that is let's say both competent
and representative that you have to
divide it according to identity
categories and first and foremost
perhaps the ones of sex and and to pick
your cabinet by genitalia is not an
acceptable technical move and exactly
the same thing happened in Canada where
25 percent of our major parties elected
officials were female but 50 percent of
the cabinet members members ended up
being female and all that means what
that certainly means is that the lead
the most qualified people were not
selected because it's statistically
impossible for them to have been
selected it was cheap virtue signalling
and and it's also technically impossible
even from the perspective of the
leftists themselves with their
intersectionality because they insist
that people have to be judged in
relationship to their oppression on
multiple dimensions simultaneously and
I've done some back-of-the-envelope
mathematical calculations and if you
have ten dimensions that mark you out
let's say as in terms of your of the
group affiliations that characterize you
then you're the only person like that in
the world
so as you multiply all you have to do is
do the math as you multiply the number
of groups that have to be given favored
status because of their hypothetically
oppressed situation then you make it
increasingly impossible for equality of
outcome to even be to to to be something
that can be practically implemented
without a bureaucracy of terrifying
proportions we also have a Ministry of
Women's Affairs in New Zealand and the
minister of Women's Affairs or the
Minister for woman as she's known
suggested recently that there were too
many white old men on boards New Zealand
of private and public companies and just
suggested that they needed to move aside
so there could be more diversity your
response to that suggestion well what's
her racial and ethnic background
just out of curiosity Leanne Genta she's
a member of our Green Party here is she
white yes well maybe it's time for her
to bloody well move aside and let
someone who isn't white have her
position all right so I'm Taiki
you don't agree with Julie and also look
they've tried this in Scandinavia where
they put you know they put quotas for
females on boards and part of the idea
was that if you did that that you would
increase the rate at which women would
move through managerial and
administrative status rankings and that
has had zero success this Anniston also
is jordyn that actually woman can
somehow up the financial performance of
ties sure
you don't believe those stats there well
there's no evidence for that
what what elevates the financial
productivity of companies is quite clear
trade conscientiousness which is a
marker for integrity and trustworthiness
and diligence ness diligence and
dutifulness is a very good predictor of
long-term economic productivity and so
is general cognitive ability and that
holds across sexes and races and the
reason for that and this is the non
racist and non sexist way of looking at
the world by the way is that there is
far more difference between individuals
within groups than there are between
groups because look the fundamental
racist sexist ethnocentric proposition
is that there are more differences
between groups of people then there are
within groups of people
yes that's essentially the racist
doctrine yeah and so we need some black
people because you know all those black
people are the same and unless we have a
voice or two from a black person then we
don't have that set of identity issues
represented well it's just simply not
the case because most of the diversity
comes at the level of individual
personality and temperament and the
literature on that is crystal clear you
know these these these are pseudo
intellectual claims made by people on
the radical left and they're very
dangerous because they're easily shifted
into the sorts of things that the
radical right likes to enjoy which is oh
I see there are immutable differences
between gender sexes and the races and
they're of substantial import and that
we we we we need to take them into
account would we're what what would you
say formulating such things as
immigration policy
so no there's no evidence that those
claims are correct and and there's
counter evidence for much of it for so
example in in Scandinavia and this is
this is as close to psychological fact
as any facts that exist is that as you
increase equality of opportunity
which means you open the doors for more
and more people and especially let's say
with regards to sex and and that's had a
big effect because of course there's far
more women in the workforce than there
than there once was you increase the
degree to which outcomes differ on
multiple dimensions and that's partly
there's a variety of reasons for that at
least a dozen and they're all important
one of which is that women especially
once they hit their 30s prefer to work
part time and that's not bad or wrong
and it's certainly not an indication of
systemic sexism so the the radical types
like to have one explanation everyone
isn't exactly the same with regards to
outcome therefore the system is a
corrupt patriarchy it's like you can
learn that in one minute in a in a
propaganda course in university and then
you have an answer for every problem
that ever besets you politically for the
rest of your life and there's no excuse
for it it's appalling scholarship I want
to come back to that point the other
thing bill proposed bill we have before
our Parliament is the idea of six
self-identification to make it easier
for people to alter their birth
certificates if they choose to identify
as anything other than the six they were
born as your views on on that sort of
legislation well the first thing I would
say it might be useful to really assess
some important problems that would be
the first thing you're dealing with an
absolutely tiny minority of people not
that that's completely without import
but the second thing is it has to be
thought through and it's not I mean I
don't know if you've been followed we
just having a little hiccup there and
we're talking to dr. Jordan B Peterson
who's joining us from Scott from Sydney
Jordan we were talking about sir sex
self-identification changes or proposed
reforms and New Zealand you said
fiercely it's a tiny number of people
affected and secondly you say we need to
think it through and what way well one
of the things that's happened for
example so really what this is is an
attempt by a certain
ideological movement to to put forth the
insistence that sex is only a
sociological construct that it's only
something learned and so that it can be
changed at whim which is also a strange
thing because if it's learned it can't
really be changed at whim and also if
it's learned it could be unlearned which
is something that the people who are
putting this legislation forward aren't
really thinking through because that
opens up the opportunity for people who
would like to reform people who would
like to change their gender back to say
normative behavior because if it's
learned it can be unlearned but more
importantly sex roles are not only
learned they're partly learned and
there's plenty of biological differences
between men and women and there and many
of them aren't trivial like men and
women are more the same than they are
different but the differences are quite
market at the extremes and so what we're
seeing partly as a consequence of this
now is the movement of say trans women
into female sports you saw this in
Minnesota just the other day I think it
was Minnesota where a newly transition
trans woman has been shattering though
weightlifting records for women's
Amorites we've hidden so she here with a
Commonwealth Games competitor it was a
form of mine it's absolutely insane you
know I mean first the fact that it's
allowed to begin with is beyond
comprehension it's a real sign of
cultural insanity and the second is that
psychologically it's almost
incomprehensible I can't imagine how you
could be a man who transformed himself
into a woman in all the ways that that's
possible and then decided to go compete
in it high level sports arena with women
who've been training their whole lives
to hit the peak of their ability and
then to absolutely bloody demolish them
say after a year of work and then to
tout that as some sort of victory for
the oppressed it's completely what's
narcissistic beyond comprehension and
it's it's well it's a sign of what
happens when you don't carefully think
things through all sorts of unexpected
consequences tend to manifest themselves
and you see the same thing happening now
with rapid onset gender dysphoria and
the treatment of very young people with
very powerful hormonal and surgical
techniques designed to permanently alter
their psychophysiological structure and
like we're gonna pay for this in a big
way in 15 years when these kids grow up
and hit adulthood and start tossing out
lawsuits as they certainly will and
should where we're going to look back
and wonder just exactly what the hell
was wrong with us so it's it's it's it's
well it's Jeff I've been by this
ideology that that's been formulated by
people like Judith Butler who absolutely
insist because they have no biological
knowledge whatsoever that all the
differences between men and women are
socially constructed it's just which is
absolutely not true true absolutely in
general Tim's Jordan and we have it in
this country and indeed everywhere we
look at the Millennial Generation
they get a bit of stick here they called
snowflakes they seem to get outraged not
only on their own behalf but on behalf
of others at the drop of a hat and they
use social media as elsewhere in the
world to call out the things they find
offensive or that their feelings do you
think there is a collective generational
psychosis occurring because of social
media
I don't know if the millennial
generation is any less sane than the
baby boomers I mean the baby boomers
have plenty of trouble and they cause
plenty of grief and misery in the 1960s
and experimented you know crazily with
psychedelic drugs and a wild lifestyle
and promiscuous sex and all of those
things and I don't think the Millennials
are any worse or any better I do think
that there is a small subset of them who
are rather dependent and rather
narcissistic and who are being
encouraged in both of those by
reprehensible adults in positions of
authority
primarily in the universities to make
the most of their victimhood feelings
and status and I do think that the
social media platforms also allow for
disproportionate effect of social effect
of people who have extreme views that
also in combination with the with the
increasing death of the of the standard
collective media which is increasingly
desperate for attention and so those
spends more and more attention paying to
people who paying spends more and more
time paying attention to people who have
extreme views on the right and the left
making exceptions that proves the rule
well it's it's possible oh I bet I mean
I've certainly been represented as an
extreme figure and that's really
something that apart from the fact that
I'm adamant in my opposition to the
radical leftists which is rather rare
among intellectuals
which brings us actually art yet rather
nicely Jordan to what I won't talk about
I ask people to call in yesterday and it
was remarkable the variety and number of
people who sent me messages and rang and
and said simply reading your book had
changed their life and can I just put a
call out if you want to talk to Jordan
we've got quarter an hour oh eight
hundred eight four four seven four seven
if you'd like to ask a question or send
a message or just say something to
Jordan you can ring him now Oh eight
hundred eight four four seven four seven
Jordan it also seems to me as much as I
see all the hatred against you and the
controversy around you online jeez
there's a lot of love there and there's
a lot of positivity and you seem to be
engaging and smiling and with young
people there's some good stuff happening
here isn't there oh yeah wait way more
than that like the the the vitriol the
triolic aspect of it is only a sporadic
bother to me usually in the aftermath of
a particularly difficult interview with
a journalist but the tour I mean I've
been to about a hundred and forty cities
now around the world and the average
audience size is well it's buried
between 2,500 and 8,000 with I would say
an average of about
2,500 to 3,000 and there the events are
unbelievably positive so most of the
time I'm surrounded by nothing but
positive responses and when I go out on
the street mm-hmm No wherever I go you
know in a typical hour I'll be stopped
by six or seven people they're usually
young men because the media has
convinced y'all well my ex is gonna say
yesterday we had just as many young
woman and middle-aged women and
middle-aged men ringing in well that's
good I think that's changed to some
degree because of the book but all of
the interactions that I have with people
on the street or in airports or so on
they're all incredibly positive people
are very polite they come up there
usually apologetic for interrupting they
introduce themselves they tell me that
watching my lectures are listening to
the audio or reading the book has
changed their life they usually tell me
a story about what's changed they have a
better let's do that in real time right
now Jordan say hello to Rachel hello
Rachel Oh
kyaa to Jordan I'm very nervous to be
talking to you and I'm gonna not very be
very good at being precise in my speech
and when I keep it very briefing to say
um thank you as all I wanted to say I'm
one of the people whose life has been
changed immeasurably by your book and
your lectures and everything that you
stand for has really had a massive
positive influence on me so I just
wanted to tell you how grateful so
what's changed it would take a very long
time to get into it but I have struggled
with mental health issues for the
majority of my life since puberty I'm
Lucy now and I've been through every
type of treatment counseling therapy
medication everything you can think of
and you know things have helped me
briefly for a little while and got
better than Chris again but your book I
guess it's the adoption of personal
responsibility more than anything else
and and the more responsibility I take
on the more I find I'm able to and the
more unable to get myself out there and
put myself in situations I wouldn't have
normally had the confidence to I'm
standing up straighter not bet gray to
keep in my room
yet but I'm working on a little things
everything just that way but the more I
take on the more the better it gets
yes well that's a good rule that's a
good rule you know that's a good
psychotherapeutic rule is the more that
you take on without overloading yourself
you know because you have to be sensible
about it the more you find that you have
abilities that will manifest themselves
that have been hidden up to that point
because of fear and avoidance and so
more power to you as far as I'm
concerned and I'm very glad to hear that
what I've been doing has been helpful
good on your right so Mary welcome thank
you very much for this opportunity I'm
doctor I was staring into the abyss and
now I'm not um I moved through my life l
purposely I consider every action and
its reaction I treat myself like I'm
someone I care for freedom it's it's
been a revelation to me encountering you
I was in a very very very dark place you
somehow I found you online unfocused
through Dave Rubin or or or whether ship
hero or or I'm not quite sure how it
happened but I've seen your lectures
I've listened till it you meant of
meaning your lectures on Genesis and
it's just been a remarkable turnaround
in my life in my family's life and I
just want to say thank you hey man I'm
thrilled to hear it so do you do you
have any sense of what in particular did
it like what was it that struck you like
I think it was just the purposeful way
that you spoke and it was just such
plain English
it was as you've described previously
there was some some rules are sort of
sort of cliches but they've they hadn't
been spoken of in a very long time and
it was as the previous caller said the
personal responsibility the the taking
care of oneself and it just struck such
a chord it was I knew some of the things
that you were saying
than before but I hadn't heard them in a
very long time my father used to say you
have strike with your shoulders back and
and finally there was a game but it was
being said in a different way and it
yeah well the thing is you need to know
why that's that's the thing and that's
what I tried to do with my lectures and
partly because I'm a behavioral
psychologist it's like we have all these
more rules and and people are told the
rules but they're very seldom given a
multi-dimensional explanation of why the
rules are necessary you know it's well
you should do it because that's what
people do or that's because you know
that's what good people do or it's your
responsibility and all those things are
true but it'd be an explanation of why
it's true and how it's related to the
responsibility that gives your life
meaning and also improves the world your
family and the community that's that's
often lacking and so that's what I was
trying to provide and it's clear and and
and and in English as clear as I could
manage it and so you know it I've tried
to make it practical and useful for
people and I'm really very very happy to
hear that it's worked for you and for
your family I'm thrilled to hear it as I
always am when I hear a story like that
Peter joins us now welcome Peter how you
doing yeah yeah hello how are you doing
Peter very very well hey um have you in
a moment of self-reflection had a look
back on this amazing and astounding
following you created and and wondered
where it's going to end up because at
the risk of sounding oxymoronic you're
probably the closest thing particularly
manatees to a messiah well I thought
about that I wouldn't say precisely in
those terms I mean one of the things I
did learn from studying Carl Jung years
ago was that if you're going to talk
about archetypal stories which I do all
the time that you have to be very
careful not to confuse yourself with the
archetype you know and so I'm I'm I'm
very cognizant of the danger of the kind
of popular
that I'm experiencing and and I do mean
the danger because the higher you fly
the faster you can fall and and you have
to be very careful to ensure that you're
not increasing the probability of that I
try to make sure that I credit other
people with many of the ideas that I
formulated and because I've learned a
lot from reading the great clinicians
and and philosophers of the last say 150
years and from my clinical practice and
so on and so and I think of this
endeavor not as something that I'm doing
but as something that we're all
collectively engaged in because I know
that you know that there's an old idea
that every person is a center of the
world and that the weight of the world
for better or worse weighs upon the
shoulders of each person and I really
believe that's true
and so if you know that then it keeps
the egotism and the arrogance down
partly out of sheer terror and it makes
it much more effective to deal with
people like when I'm lecturing in front
of an audience I'm not lecturing to them
you know I'm lecturing with them talking
about problems that we all have
including me and aims that we all all
need to develop including me and you
have to include yourself so to speak
among the sinners and the and the
reprehensible types in order to
communicate with people properly and I
do my best to ensure that I'm starkly
aware of my shortcomings and faults at
every moment I can possibly manage and I
have family and friends who also help
keep what I'm doing in check and and to
make sure that it's not going sideways
in some manner that's you know where I'm
taking things for granted or becoming
arrogant or any of that and so so far
that's worked out well and hopefully it
will continue to JA welcome to the
program oh hi Joe thanks talking with me
Jordan
all right you how are you doing good
thank you so I'm a young academic in New
Zealand and one of the problems were one
of the obsessions I would say we have in
universities is a Ferguson
race and gender so I'm I would call it a
centrist position somewhat liberal
minded but what advice would you give a
young academic pushing against what I
see is the far less the gender of the
universities well the first thing I
would say is they're a lot more moderate
types of your sort than you think and so
if you're a careful person and you're
thinking things through and you have
things to object to you can be sure
virtually sure that a majority of people
agree with you even though they're too
cowed let's say to to speak up I would
say get your thoughts in order you know
so you know what you stand for and then
I would also say don't agree with
anything that you don't agree with
because all that'll happen and you're a
young academic all that will happen if
you compromise your intellectual soul
like increment by increment over the
next ten years is that you will end up
alcoholic and bitter hating your job
despised by your undergraduates and
absolutely sick of your existence and
like you got to keep that really firmly
in mind because every time you're called
upon to stand forth for something you
believe in it's a it's a test of
character and courage and it's easy to
put it off because it's a lot of trouble
you know it's a lot of conflict and you
might think oh god do I really have to
go through with this I've got other
things to do and if the answer is well I
better stand up for what I believe in
now because if I keep letting it go
increment by increment for the next ten
years I'm going to end up in a position
that that is absolutely dreadful
you know you'll be much older than you
need to be and all of the thrill that
should be part of teaching young people
and doing research and staying on the
cutting edge of knowledge all of that
will have been taken away by the
ideologue who already know everything
and insist that they get to regular hey
what you
think and say so I'd have the small
fights one by one value other lucky
lasted the caller's Jordans with yet
yeah dr. Jordan Peterson you are awesome
man already books we were following you
I'm assuming psychology and philosophy
myself I did a degree and I'm doing my
post office here and a lot of what you
say you know there's a wee bit of
Nietzsche in there and I'm is you know
and I totally agree because we live in a
society where what for me I often say
what I think and I have to moderate that
but particularly today in our society
when you do that you're in way more
trouble for offending someone or
something and I love the fact that you
kind of get it out there and I wish that
you know I had that opportunity to just
and get it out and people didn't even
get over one one question I was wanting
to ask you though I mean I'm a I'm a
Christian but I studied Marcus Aurelius
and I read his book and I fear those
books are you into stole isn't um not I
wouldn't say specifically lots of people
who have been studying stoicism have
talked to me and suggested that I should
be the overlap I think is that the stoic
virtues have been radically under played
in our society because we have this idea
that life is easy and that we should be
happy and well first of all life isn't
easy and perhaps we should be happy but
there's lots of times when we're not
going to be in Jordan alright I hate to
break this up but coming up to the news
we've got calls stacked up I'm hoping to
meet you when you come here and I'd like
to invite you now if you get any spare
time in your schedule to come under the
studio because that's really our boards
of fill with people who want to talk to
you I also want to thank you enormous
Lee for your time today and for assuring
us that you will not you know lead to
the deal visit will not leave to the
downfall of New Zealand civilization as
we know it well I hope I hope I think
you have quite a civilization and that
would I'd hate to be the bringer of its
downfall
oh well hope that doesn't happen lovey
told you Jordan thank you very much for
your time
dr. John Bank you turn the interview
first of all if you don't have a purpose
sensor it isn't that your life becomes
neutral in a meaningless sense it's that
your life becomes characterized by
unbearable suffering because the
baseline condition of life is something
like unbearably suffering